{"tossups": [{"question": "Rebel officers from this empire brutally killed 72 prominent intellectuals in another country in the Slaughter of the Knezes. This empire\u2019s military defeated Uros the Weak at the Battle of Maritsa in 1371; eighteen years later, Prince Lazar and a leader of this opposing empire were each killed at the Field of Blackbirds. Murad I led this empire at the Battle of Kosovo. For ten points, name this Islamic power whose sultans controlled Serbia from Constantinople.", "answer": "<b> Ottoman</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A fleet of 49 ships on the victorious side of this battle was commanded by Charles Saunders. Members of the 78th Highlanders were able to make a surprise landing the night before this battle because one side was expecting a supply convoy. A general at this battle claimed that only 100 men were needed to guard L\u2019Anse au Foulon. For ten points, name this battle in the Canadian theater of the Seven Years\u2019 War where the Marquis de Montcalm and James Wolfe, the generals of the opposing sides, were both killed.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Quebec</b> (accept Battle of the<b> Plains of Abraham</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this man who won the first presidential election after World War II and succeeded Franklin Roosevelt.", "answer": "Harry<b> Truman</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A poem written during this period describes the sound of war vehicles as they approach the battle field; that poem is \u201cThe Song of Wagons.\u201d Another poet during this period allegedly drowned after drunkenly trying to hug the reflection of the moon in a pond. Du Fu and Li Bai wrote during the rule of this dynasty, which faced the An Lushan Rebellion under Emperor Xuanzong. Empress Wu established the Second Zhou dynasty during, for ten points, what Chinese dynasty that existed between the Sui and Song dynasties?", "answer": "<b> Tang</b> Dynasty Page 1", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "According to myth, a king named Tuu Ku Ihu moved these objects with the help of a fertility god. Many of these objects were toppled after they were discovered by Jacob Roggeveen. Several of these objects, which were often topped with a topknot structure called a pukao, are found at a site called Ahu Akivi. One of these objects at the British Museum is called Hoa Hakananai\u2019a, and these objects were often set on stone platforms called ahu. The Rapa Nui people worshiped, for ten points, what stone heads on Easter Island?", "answer": "<b> Moai</b> statues (prompt on descriptions of the stone heads on Easter Island before it is read)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This ship\u2019s second to last captain, Daniel Dow, resigned from stress after the Louis and Laverock failed to escort it. The<em> Juno</em> arrived too late to rescue this ship\u2019s passengers, which included Alfred Vanderbilt. Failure to follow a zig-zag pattern may have led to this ship\u2019s sinking. William Jennings Bryan resigned after the downing of this ship, which was carrying 50 tons of shell casings at the time it was destroyed in the North Atlantic. 128 Americans drowned on this ship. For ten points, the United States entered World War I after what ship was torpedoed by a U-Boat?", "answer": "RMS<b> Lusitania</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This group\u2019s second and final leader was Robert Greim, who was appointed to his post after covertly traveling to Tiergarten with Hanna Reitsch. This force, which was greatly expanded by Walter Wever and Albert Kesselring, employed the Ju-87 in Spain as part of the Condor Legion that bombed Guernica. Operation Sealion was canceled when this group was defeated by the RAF in the Battle of Britain. Hermann Goring led, for ten points, what Nazi air force?", "answer": "<b> Luftwaffe</b> (prompt on descriptions of the Nazi German air force before the end)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This leader narrowly avoided capture at Drvar when he was targeted in Operation Knight\u2019s Move. This leader had been forced to cooperate with Draza Mihailovic, the head of the Chetnik movement, in a guerrilla conflict. This European leader served as the first Secretary-General of the Non-Aligned Movement after he was expelled from Cominform by Joseph Stalin. This leader rose to prominence leading the Partisan movement in World War II. For ten points, name this marshal who led communist Yugoslavia.", "answer": "Josip<b> Broz Tito</b> (accept either or both names)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This politician, who implemented a program of forced sterilizations, was eventually succeeded by a man who was assassinated in 1991 by the Tamil Tigers. After this politician authorized Operation Blue Star, her own Sikh bodyguards assassinated her in 1984. For ten points, name this first female Prime Minister of India.", "answer": "<b> I</b>ndira<b> Gandhi</b> (prompt on Gandhi)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Name either son.", "answer": "<b> Sanjay</b> Gandhi and/or<b> Rajiv</b> Gandhi (prompt on Gandhi) Page 3", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The outcome of this conflict led Mark Twain to angrily write \u201cThe War Prayer.\u201d During this conflict, Charles Eagan was criticized for poisoning troops by providing \u201cembalmed beef.\u201d The order \u201cyou may fire when ready, Gridley\u201d was given during a decisive naval victory in this conflict during which one only American under George Dewey died. The yellow journalism of William Randolph Hearst fueled sentiment for, for ten points, what \u201csplendid little war\u201d that began after the<em> Maine</em> sank in Havana Harbor in 1898?", "answer": "<b> Spanish-American</b> War (accept<b> Philippine-American</b> War until \u201cembalmed\u201d is read, and prompt on it thereafter)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A politician with this last name used \u201cunparliamentary language\u201d while addressing John Lundrigan in the House of Commons in what became known as the \u201cFuddle Duddle\u201d incident. Photos of another politician with this last name wearing blackface at an Arabian Nights gala surfaced in September of 2019; that politician\u2019s party lost their majority in 2019 elections. For ten points, give this last name of Pierre and Justin, a father-son pair of Canadian Prime Ministers.", "answer": "<b> Trudeau</b> (accept Pierre and/or Justin<b> Trudeau</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Early kings of these people like Euric conquered southern Gaul, defeated the Alans, and forced the Vandals into north Africa. The Gaullic possessions of this group were later taken by the Franks, and later kings like Roderic spent their time fighting each other, then lost their kingdom to the Moors. Rome was sacked in 410 AD by, for ten points, what barbarian tribe, the western branch of the Goths?", "answer": "<b> Visigoth</b>s (prompt on \u201cGoths\u201d)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This dynasty\u2019s greatest ruler rose to power on the \u201cNight of the Three Caliphs,\u201d named because his son Mamun was born while the king Hadi died. This dynasty was established</b> <b>following a battle at the Great (+)</b> <b>Zab in which its founder, as-Saffah, prevailed. A river</b> <b>allegedly ran black with ink from destroyed books after (*)</b> Hulagu Khan sacked this dynasty\u2019s capital and desecrated the House of Wisdom that had been built by Harun al-Rashid. For ten points, name this caliphate that lasted until the 13th century in Baghdad.", "answer": "<b> Abbasid</b> Caliphate", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Many hypotheses about this event were strengthened by a 2016 project to drill into the only extant peak ring on Earth; the drilling found pink granite and shocked quartz. The</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Alvarez family studied this event and posed the most prominent hypothesis about its</b> <b>origins. This event is often known as the \u201cK-T event\u201d for the symbols for the eras of geologic time it separates. A (*) </b> meteor impact at what is now the Yucatan Peninsula probably caused, for ten points, what event that, roughly 66 million years ago, wiped out nearly all large reptiles on Earth?", "answer": "<b> Cretaceous-Tertiary extinction</b> event (accept<b> Cretaceous-Paleogene extinction</b> event; accept<b> K-T</b> (or<b> K-Pg</b>)<b> extinction</b> event before \u201cK-T\u201d is mentioned; accept descriptions of \u201cthe<b> end of the dinosaurs</b>\u201d)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Earth Science"}, {"question": "<b>One side in this battle was aided by domineering artillery fire from Combs\u2019 Hill. Charles Lee was court-martialed for failing to secure a decisive outcome in this battle, which failed</b> <b>to prevent Henry (+)</b> <b>Clinton from withdrawing to New York. During the second day of</b> <b>this battle, artilleryman William Hays collapsed of (*)</b> heatstroke and his wife, Mary Hays, took his place loading the cannon, a feat that is often conflated with her transporting water to soldiers. For ten points, name this 1778 Revolutionary War battle that spawned the myth of Molly Pitcher.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Monmouth</b> Courthouse", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>After being unable to succeed his father\u2019s throne, this figure became King of Tiryns by swapping thrones with his cousin Megapenthes. When invading Greece, Xerxes the First claimed that the Persian people were descendants of this figure. This figure accidentally</b> <b>killed his grandfather, (+)</b> <b>Acrisius, with a discus, as was prophesied. Using a body part</b> <b>from a previous victim, this figure killed the sea monster (*)</b> Cetus to rescue Andromeda. For ten points, name this Greek hero, who used an invisibility cap and Hermes\u2019 sandals to kill Medusa.", "answer": "<b> Perseus</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b>Carole Pateman argued that this concept leads to the patriarchal domination of women. A work titled for this concept claims that countries in hot climates are more likely to be monarchies and notes that the power of the state is split between the (+) government and the people, who represent the general will. The line \u201cMan is (*)</b> born free; and everywhere he is in chains\u201d opens a work titled for, for ten points, what political relationship in which people agree to be ruled by the state, discussed in a namesake book by Jean-Jacques Rousseau?", "answer": "<b> social contract</b> Page 9", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b>During this century, Ruy L\u00b4opez de Villalobos came up with the name for the Philippines. Juan de Sep\u00b4ulveda engaged in a debate at Valladolid over the definition of natural slavery with Bartolome de las Casas during this century. The (+) Revolt of the Comuneros occurred in this century, during which Joanna the Mad\u2019s son ruled. Holy Roman Emperor Charles (*) </b>V supported the Council of Trent during this century and funded the expedition of Ferdinand Magellan. For ten points, name this century that began eight years after the first voyage of Christopher Columbus.", "answer": "<b> 1500s</b> (accept<b> 16th</b> century)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man was sued by the family of Rene Schneider after this man\u2019s order to stand down led to the kidnapping and death of Schneider. This man was replaced by Brent Scowcroft as National Security Advisor during the \u201cHalloween (+) Massacre\u201d in Gerald Ford\u2019s cabinet. For his role in seeking a \u201cpeace with honor,\u201d a Nobel Peace Prize was awarded to this man and (*) </b> Le Duc Tho, who declined the award. This man negotiated with Zhou Enlai to orchestrate a visit to Mao Zedong in China. For ten points, name this man who served as Richard Nixon\u2019s Secretary of State.", "answer": "Henry<b> Kissinger</b>  (1) <b>This man screamed \u201cI don\u2019t care about my dignity!\u201d at a heckler during a</b> <b>campaign tour attended by assistants like Postmaster General Alexander Randall. This man, who served in the Senate after leaving the White House, lost support after</b> <b>comparing himself to Jesus Christ in his (+)</b> <b>\u201cSwing Around the Circle\u201d speeches.</b> <b>Edmund Ross cast the deciding vote that allowed this man to stay in office after he controversially (*)</b> removed Edwin Stanton as Secretary of War, violating the Tenure of Office Act. For ten points, name this president who survived an impeachment trial after succeeding the assassinated Abraham Lincoln. ANSWER: Andrew<b> Johnson</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}